# File: artifact.txt


# This file is used to initialize the 'artifact' information for the NPPMoria game.

# Do not modify this file unless you know exactly what you are doing,
# unless you wish to risk possible system crashes and broken savefiles.

# The artifact indexes are defined in 'defines.h', and must not be changed.


# === Understanding artifact.txt ===

# N: serial number : item name
# I: tval : sval : pval
# W: depth : rarity : weight : cost
# P: base armor class : base damage : plus to-hit : plus to-dam : plus to-ac
# F: flag | flag | etc
# A: activation : recharge time : recharge time dice
# D: Description

# 'N' indicates the beginning of an entry. The serial number must
# increase for each new item.

# 'I' is for basic information. The tval is for the type of item, the
# sval identifies the subtype and the pval indicates the amount of
# effect the item has, if applicable.

# 'W' is for extra information. Depth is the depth the object is
# normally found at, rarity determines how common the object is,
# weight is in tenth-pounds and cost is the item's value.

# 'P' is for power information. The items base armor class, its base
# damage and pluses to-hit, to-dam and to-ac.

# 'F' is for flags. These are fairly self-explanatory. As many F:
# lines may be used as are needed to specify all the flags and flags
# are separated by the '|' symbol.

# 'A' is for activation.  Activation is the effect the artifact
# activates for. The recharge time calculates from the recharge time
# plus a random value between 1 and the recharge time dice (if not 0).
# If an activation is given then the artifact must also have the
# ACTIVATE flag.

# 'D' is for description. As many D: lines may be used as needed to get a
# complete description of the artifact. The description will be shown
# if an identified artifact is 'I'nspected.

### IMPORTANT NOTES ###
# (1.) Any changes or additions to the file will have influence on randarts
# and may break savefile compatibility for old savegames with randarts.  If
# using random artifacts, finish your existing game before making any
# changes to the artifact.txt file at all.
# (2.) Removing any artifact, or changing its 'base' type (as defined by
# the tval and sval entries in the 'I:' line), will break savefile
# compatibility for ALL savefiles.
# (3.) Adding a new artifact, or changing the powers of existing ones, will
# NOT affect savefile compatibility for games with the standard artifact set:
# it is perfectly safe to do this. (If your new artifact is a new kind of
# object, or a new one at the end of the file, you must also amend object.txt
# or limits.txt.)

# (4.) Accented characters may be used in an artifact's name or description.
# Use the proper code, enclosed between square brackets, to enter an accented
# character. For example: L['u]thien or L[uacute]thien are both valid ways to
# get an acute accent on the u in Luthien. All valid codes can be found in
# util.c.


# Here is the list of 'Special' artifacts - The Phial


# The Phial of Galadriel

N:1:of Galadriel
I:39:4:0
W:3:3:10:10000
P:0:1d1:0:0:0
F:IGNORE_ACID | IGNORE_ELEC | IGNORE_FIRE | IGNORE_COLD | ACTIVATE
F:INSTA_ART
A:ILLUMINATION:10:10
D:A small crystal phial, with the light of Eärendil's Star contained
D: inside.  Its light is imperishable, and near it darkness cannot
D: endure.

