# File: quest.txt

# This file is used to initialize the "lib/data/quest.raw" file, which is
# used to initialize the "quest" information for the Angband game.

# Do not modify this file unless you know exactly what you are doing,
# unless you wish to risk possible system crashes and broken savefiles.

# Note that you can either put in a monster index, OR a unique index.
# Inserting both means that the unique index will be ignored.

# Format:
# N:<quest index>:<quest name>
# W:<level>:<monster>:UNUSED:<number>

# This slot for the adventurer's guild quests.  This must be 0, as it is hard coded in 
# the source code
N:0:Guild quest
W:0:0:0:0

N:1:Sauron
W:99:681:0:1

N:2:Morgoth
W:100:682:0:1
