As you turn to leave the dank cavern and crawl up a tunnel towards
 the surface, you check to make sure you have equipped your gear and
 have a method of healing yourself, escaping from danger and damaging
 monsters. You also need to insure you have spent some time training
 with your weapon of choice! 

The memory of long, magnetic eyes with a true cat-green fire that
 burns from within drives you forward and up from the center of the
 earth. . .

(Get help by pushing '?') ('w'eild weapons and items by pushing 'w')
('q'uaff healing tonics to cure wounds)
('r'ig mechanisms of phase door and etheric travel to flee danger)
(use a weapon, martial arts, firearms, spellbooks, classpowers, or
 enigmatic devices to damage enemies)

(To train with your weapons 'G'ain skill points! Hit 'G' to distribute
 skill points and 'h'op between the three categories of skill points
 -- '?' when a skill is highlighted will give you information about
 that skill)